<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two speeches of George Earl of Bristol with some observations upon them by which it may appear whether or no the said Earl deserve to be involved in the common calamity brought upon Roman Catholicks, by the folly and presumption of some few factious papists.</title>
            <title>Speeches. Selections</title>
            <author>Bristol, George Digby, Earl of, 1612-1677.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77535</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4786A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201146</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097576</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097576</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171188</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77535)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171188)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2566:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two speeches of George Earl of Bristol with some observations upon them by which it may appear whether or no the said Earl deserve to be involved in the common calamity brought upon Roman Catholicks, by the folly and presumption of some few factious papists.</title>
                  <title>Speeches. Selections</title>
                  <author>Bristol, George Digby, Earl of, 1612-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page 9-12 are cropped with some loss of print</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  England.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Catholic Church.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171188:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Two Speeches, Of GEORGE Earl of <hi>Briſtol</hi> With ſome obſervations upon them By which it may appear whether or no the ſaid Earl deſerve to be involved in the Common Calamity brought upon Roman Catholicks, by the folly and preſumption of ſome few factious PAPISTS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed in the Year, 1674,</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:171188:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171188:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEing a Roman Catholick agreeing in principles with what <hi>George</hi> Earl of <hi>Briſtol</hi> hath of late publickly declared of himſelf in Parliament, I could hardly bear with patience the injurious cenſures and uncharitable conſtructions made of a ſpeech of the ſaid Honourable perſons, in the houſe of Peers, by divers of the ſame Communion, though of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſtamp in relation to government.</p>
            <p>They did their beſt to have it underſtood, that the perſecution which ſeem'd to threaten Catholicks, had whetted that Earl's wit to find out ſpecious and plauſible diſtinctions betwixt Catholick and Catholick, whereby to exempt himſelf from the inconveniences likely to fall upon the generality of that profeſſion; Diſtinctions which in themſelves they ſaid had no ſolid grounds of diſcrimination, and that his ſentiments expreſs'd therein, were adapted only to the preſent occaſion.</p>
            <p>The publiſhing of the ſaid Speech in Print I thought would be a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to the Publick, as well as a juſtice to that Lord, wherein his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of Catholicks of the Church of Rome, from Catholicks of the Court of Rome, will certainly appear a right and a reaſonable one: Concerning which, if the reader reſt not ſatisfied, but will needs deſcend to particular differences, he is referred to a dedication of a book lately publiſhed in print, and directed to all Catholicks of His Majeſties Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, by one <hi>Peter Walſh,</hi> a Franciſcan Fryer, wherein the chief impoſals of the Court of Rome upon the more orthodox Doctrines of the Church of Rome, are faithfully and learnedly expoſed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171188:3"/>
            <p>Now as to the ſecond part of their detraction, I thought the injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of it could not better be made appear, then by Printing alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Speech of the ſaid Earl's, made to the houſe of Commons many years ſince, wherein the ſelfſame ſentiments were eminently declared by him, at a time when Roman Catholicks were as free from alarums of any new perſecution, as ever they have been during any Seſſion of Parliament.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171188:3"/>
            <head>A Speech of <hi>George</hi> Earl of <hi>Briſtol's</hi> made in the houſe of Peers at the firſt reading of the Bill againſt Popery, upon <hi>Saturday</hi> the fifteenth of <hi>March,</hi> 1673.</head>
            <head type="sub">The King being then preſent.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I am very ſenſible to what inconveniences a man of my perſwaſion ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes himſelf that offers to ſpeak (eſpecially to break the Ice firſt) to a Bill of this nature brought up to you from the great repreſentative of the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> a Bill which thoſe of my own profeſſion may poſſibly think ſo ſevere, and moſt Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants ſo neceſſary. If I ſpeake for the paſſing of this Bill it is likely I may give ſcandal to the firſt and if I ſpeak againſt the paſſing of it it is certain I shall give high provocation to the latter. And if I ſpeak for ſome parts of it and againſt ſome others, I may have cauſe to fear that I may offend both ſides, the uſual fate of thoſe who affect to shew their ſubtilty by cutting a Feather (as we ſay) well my Lords ſo be it, let what will befall me upon this occaſion I shall ſtill have within me a conſolation above even the power of an Act of Parliament to take from me I mean the teſtimony of a good Conſcience, and of having
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171188:4"/>diſcharged the duty of a Peer of this houſe in ſo eminent a conjuncture clearly, and candidly according to the beſt of my underſtanding. Yet ſtill with moſt humble ſubmiſſion to the ſuperiority of yours.</p>
            <p>My Lords, before I enter upon the matter give me leave to tell thoſe Lords of my own Profeſſion that hear me what I think their duty as well as mine if any of them ſhall think fit to ſpeak in this houſe upon this occaſion.</p>
            <p>My Lords, I do underſtand that how different ſo ever our ſentiments are from your Lordſhips in point of Doctrine, and queſtions ſpiritual, we ought to lay the conſideration of them all aſide in this place, and to ſpeak in it not as <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks,</hi> but as faithful members of a Proteſtant Parliament. And as ſuch give a preferrence before all temporal intereſts of our own to the right intereſt of the State under whoſe protection we live, reſting confident that whatever part of our eaſe and conveniences in this world, we ſhall willingly ſacrifice to the Peace, and ſecurity of our Countrey will one way, or other be recompenſed unto us by Almighty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God, either in this, or in the other.</p>
            <p>Now my Lords, as to the reſt of this moſt honourable aſſembly give me leave to remind you what kind of Catholick I told you the other day I am, that is a Catholick of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> not a Catholick of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> A diſtinction (if I am not much deceived) worthy of your memory and reflection, when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any ſevere proceeding againſt thoſe whom you call Papiſts ſhall come in queſtion, ſince Catholicks of the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> do only deſerve that name.</p>
            <p>My Lords, I could eaſily make clear unto you the reality, and the reaſonableneſs of this diſtinction by inſtances in matter of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, did I not think it always impertinent to trouble this houſe with points of controverſie, but I ſhall only take the liberty to evidence the juſtneſs of the diſtinction to you by a Perſonal inſtance, <hi>Fra. Paule</hi> my Lords who writ ſo ſhrewdly the Hiſtory
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171188:4"/>of the Counſel of <hi>Trent</hi> I am ſure will never paſs with any body that hath read him for a Catholick of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> the artifices and abuſes of which he hath expoſed to the world in ſuch lively colours and painted them out in Figures (give me leave to ſay) even bigger then the life, and yet this <hi>Fra. Paulo</hi> my Lords dyed piouſly, and devoutly a ſteady Catholick of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſuch as I truſt God will give me the grace to do were I put to the bloodieſt tryal, ſuch a Catholick my Lords I am, and as ſuch I make no doubt but I ſhall live to do <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> more ſervice, and procure them more advantages from the comiſeration of this Parliament, then all the unquiet ſpirits, or rabbi-buſies of the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now my Lords, I come to ſpeak to the matter of this Bill, which I shall do at this time generally, and at large, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving my ſelf as to perticulars till it be read by Paragraphs, yet thus much I cannot forbear telling you now that there are ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular in this Bill, as thoſe of the Queens, and Duke of <hi>Yorks</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick ſervants, which while I have a tongue to ſpeak, and a right to uſe it here I shall ever oppoſe until I shall find my ſelf bound up by your Lordships determination</p>
            <p>In the firſt place my Lords, I beſeech you to conſider, that this Bill for the ſecuring of general fears, is brought up to you from the houſe of Commons, the great repreſentative of the people, and conſequently the beſt Judges of the true temper of the Nation; A houſe of Commons ſurpaſſing all that ever hath been, in the illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious marks of their duty, loyalty, and affection to their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> both in his Perſon and government. Such a houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons as His Majeſtie ought to conſider, and cherish always, with ſuch a kind of love as is due to a VVife, never to be parted with unkindly and not as to a Miſtriſs, to be turned off when our turn is ſerved by her.</p>
            <p>My Lords, this caſual mention of a VVife, ſuggeſts to my thoughts a purſuance of the compariſon, apt enough methinks,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171188:5"/>I have obſerved in the courſe of my life, that men who have VVives ſomewhat coquettes, that is a little ſubject to gallantrys live eaſier lives with them, and freer from troubleſome contentions then thoſe who have VVives of exact and rigid vertue, and the reaſon of it is clear: For the more gameſome Dames being conſcious of their failings in that eſſential part are carefull to diſguiſe, and repair them by kind and tender compliances with their Husbands humour in all other things, whereas VVives ſeverely punctual and exact in the chief Matrimonial duty, expect and even exact far greater compliances from their Husbands, and think themſelves as it were priviledged by the rigidneſs of their vertue to be ſomtimes troubleſome in domeſtick affairs; But eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if Jealouſie be (<hi>en campagne</hi> as the French phraſe is) In like manner my Lords, it is not to be much wondred at, if this incomparable houſe of Commons, tranſcending all that ever was in the grand eſſentials of duty, loyalty, and affection to their King, should be at ſometimes a little troubleſome to him in leſſer occurrences, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when once fears and jealouſies are on wing. My Lords I shall not pretend to determine whether there hath been uny juſt grounds given or no by the rabbi-buſies aforementioned, or by the unſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ambition of any <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> for ſuch fears and jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, It ſuffices to exact the neceſſity of a timely remedy that they have indeed moſt violently ſeized, and diſtempred the minds of the Major part of His Majeſties Proteſtant ſubjects, which certainly no man converſant in the world can deny. Now my Lords, in popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar fears, and apprehenſions, thoſe uſually prove moſt dangerous that are raiſed upon grounds not well underſtood, and may be rightly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled to the fatal effects of panick fears in Armies, where I have ſeldome ſeen great diſorders arrive from intelligences brought in by parties, and by ſcouts, or by Advertiſements to Generals, But from alarums upon groundleſs, and capritious fears of danger, taken up we know not either how, or why, no man of moderate experience in military affairs but hath found at one time or other, the dangerous effects, in the giving a ſtop to which miſchiefs, the skill of great Commanders is beſt ſeen. In like manner my Lords, this great and, juditious aſſembly of the houſe of Commons rightly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171188:5"/>ſenſible of the dangerous effects which ſo general a diſturbance of mens minds in the concernments of Religion (how groundleſs ſoever) might produce, have applied their cares to obviate them by this Bill; a Bill in my opinion as full of moderation towards Catholicks, as of prudence, and ſecurity towards the Religion of the State.</p>
            <p>In this Bill my Lords, notwithſtanding all the alarums of the encreaſe of <hi>Popery</hi> and deſigns of Papiſts, here is no mention of barring them from private, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt exerciſe of their Religion; no baniſhing them to ſuch a diſtance from Court, no putting in execution of penal Laws in force againſt them, all their precautions are reduced to this one intent natural to all ſocieties of men, of hindring a leſſer oppoſite party from growing too ſtrong for the greater and more conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable one, and in this way of juſt prevention, is not the moderation of the houſe of Commons to be admired; that they have reſtrained it to this ſole point, of debarring their adverſaries from offices, and places; and from acceſſions of wealth by favour of the Soveraign; They conſidered well that wealth and power from publique charges and imployments do range the generality of men to opinions, and parties more ſtrongly farr, then all other arguments, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſaying of <hi>Eneas Silvius</hi> (himſelf a <hi>Pope</hi>) That the <hi>Popes</hi> ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority over general Counſels would ever find moſt Doctors for it, becauſe the <hi>Pope</hi> had ſo many Biſhop-ricks to give, the Counſells none. I ſay my Lords, that in contemplation hereof, the wiſdome of the houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons has wholly applyed its care in this Bill to hinder (as appears moſt reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able) thoſe of an oppoſite party, from a Part in the government of that State, under whoſe protection they live.</p>
            <p>It is true my Lords, ſome <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> may ſeem to be put to extraordinary teſts in this Act, and ſuch as upon the ſcore of Conſcience as a <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> I ſhall give my negative to, but ſpeaking as a member of a Proteſtant Parliament. I cannot but think prudent, and reaſonable in the propoſers, their end being ſolidly to ſecure the fears of thoſe they repreſent. And after all my Lords, how few do the ſharp tryals, and teſts of this Act regard? only a few ſuch <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> as would fain hold offices, and places at the price of hypocriſie, and diſſimulation of their true ſentiments in Religion. My Lords I am none of thoſe, none of thoſe wherry-men in Religion, who look one way and row another. I have had the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to exerciſe a great charge of ſtate under the laſt King of bleſſed memory, and to continue the ſame under our moſt gratious Soveraign that is now, till it pleaſed Almighty God to call me (even at the Article of death) to that Religion, wherein I truſt he will give me the grace to live and dye, what danger ſoever may be ſet before me; But after that call my firſt work my Lords, was to deliver up the Seals to the King uncomanded, as judging it unfit (though then in a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Countrey) for any man of a different Religion from his Prince, to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe a charge of that importance under him, and I am now my Lords much more of that opinion then ever.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:171188:6"/>
Upon the whole matter my Lords, however the ſentiments of a Catholick of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (I ſtill ſay not of the Court of <hi>Rome)</hi> may obliege me (upon ſcruple of Conſcience) in ſome perticulars of this Bill, to give my negative to it when it comes to the paſſing, yet as a member of a Proteſtant Parliament my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice prudentially cannot but go along with the main ſcope of it. The preſent cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of time, and affairs conſidered, and the neceſſity of compoſing the diſturbed minds of the people.</p>
            <p>It may be ſaid my Lords, that ſome things in this Bill ſeem to trench upon His Majeſties Prerogative, and his inherent power of pardoning and ſuſpending proſecutions.</p>
            <p>My Lords, that Inherent power in our Soveraign, God forbid any body ſhould think this moſt meriting houſe of Commons could ever have the leaſt deſign of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away, or invalidating, But to deſire His Majeſty to ſuſpend the application of that undeniable power, in certain particular caſes, I eſteem to be farr from any derogation to the eſſence of that royal prerogative.</p>
            <p>My Lords, let me give you an inſtance to make my ſentiments of this matter more clear, His Majeſty recomended unto you in a former ſeſſion, the care to provide a Bill for preventing the great miſchief by duells<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if your Lordſhips ſhould have thought ſit in that Bill to have engaged His Majeſty to have declared that he would never pardon any duel, would it have been though a derogation to the inherent regal powers of pardoning? when as the cure of ſo great an evil could never be hoped for whilſt there was room left to a Princes pitty, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity, to be wrought upon in favour of ſuch gallant Perſons who are moſt uſually involved in that crime? No my Lords, when Nations are ſo happy as to have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more to fear then from the good nature, and debonair inclinations of their Prince there can in my opinion no better ſervice bed one him, then by way of a dutiful adreſs, ſometimes to obliege him to a binding up of his own hands from the exerciſe of thoſe indulgent vertues, which in perticular caſes, may prove noxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Publique.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:171188:6"/>
            <head>A Speech of the Earl of <hi>Briſtol's</hi> to the houſe of Commons ſpoken by him there, on the faſt of <hi>July,</hi> 1673.</head>
            <head type="sub">Being a vindication of himſelf, and of Sir <hi>Richard Temple.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>M. Speaker,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ere I to be wrought upon by the arts or menaces of my enemies, or by the alarums in my behalf of my friends contrary to that firmneſs and aſſurance which a cleer heart and a good conſcience do always uphold in a man of honour, I ſhould have appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in this place with ſuch fear and trembling as could not chuſe but diſorder any mans reaſon and elocution.</p>
            <p>The niceneſs of the ſubject upon which I am brought hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were enough to diſcompoſe, but over and above that, I am not ignorant what Perſonal prejudices I am under, and how induſtriouſly they have been improved among you.</p>
            <p>But Mr. Speaker, when I look round this illuſtrious aſſembly and ſee above three parts of it compoſed of men that wear as I do a Sword by their ſide, and have drawn it ſo often in His Majeſties ſervice, Gentlemen of birth integrity, and fortune, all apprehenſions vaniſh from a man that hath ſerved and ſuffered for the King as I have done.</p>
            <p>Mr. Speaker I know the time of this honourable houſe, upon whoſe prudent deliberations the happineſs of King and Kingdom depends, is too pretious to have any part of it ſpent in vindication of me; But ſince not only the reputation and the innocence of one of your members depends upon what I ſhall ſay, but even his Majeſties honour is in ſome ſort concerned in the right apprehenſion of it, I hope it will be thought no preſumption in me to begg of you, as I do in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, one quarter of an hours patience and attention.</p>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, I am here expoſ'd as the bearer of a meſſage to His Majeſty from Sir <hi>Richard Temple,</hi> which he hath thought worthy to be complaind of to this houſe, and which Sir <hi>R. T.</hi> affirms that he never ſent.</p>
            <p>Lay your hands upon your hearts Gentlemen, and ſay truly; does not your innate candor pitty a perſon of my condition brought into a ſtrait in all appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance ſo inextricable? For on the one ſide if I avow to have carried from Sir R. <hi>T.</hi> that meſſage, which His Majeſty hath made ſo high and ſo unuſual an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of his being offended at, and which Sir R. <hi>T.</hi> denies to have ever ſent? How can men of honour ever forgive me ſo ungentlemanly a proceeding towards a Perſon who had truſted me as a friend with the doing him as he thought a good
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171188:7"/>office with His Majeſty. On the other ſide Mr. Speaker ſhould I diſavow the having delivered the meſſage from Sir R. <hi>T.</hi> which His Majeſty hath thought fit to affirm that he received from him, and by me, what ſubject can be ſtrong enough not to ſink for ever under the weight of ſuch a contradiction to his Soveraign? I ask you again Gentlemen, does not the condition I am brought into by the arts of mine enemies, move at the ſame time your pitty and your indignation.</p>
            <p>Mr, Speaker, when <hi>David</hi> was put to his choice of one of the three ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Calamities he made election of the Plague, and why? <hi>That he might fall into the hand of the Lord, and not into the hands of Men.</hi> In like manner Mr. Speaker, if one of the two extreams that threaten me be as it appears unavoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, let me fall into the hand of Gods Vicegerent the King.</p>
            <p>The world would never pardon me an unworthy action, His Princely good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I am ſure would in time pardon me a generous fault; But when you have heard me our Gentlemen I am confident that you will find that I ſhall need nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the worlds pardon, nor the Kings, but only yours.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place Mr. Speaker, I am bound to clear Sir R. <hi>T.</hi> which I here do upon my honour, that he never ſent by me any meſſage to the King that had the leaſt tincture in it of an undertaking of his, which I conceive to be the only part that could give offence to His Majeſty, or be a ground for the complaint made againſt him.</p>
            <p>In the next place, ſince the King (who the Law ſays can do no wrong) hath thought fit to affirm that I brought him that undertaking meſſage from Sir R. <hi>T.</hi> It muſt needs be true, and I do with all ſubmiſſion acknowledge whatſoever His Majeſty is pleaſed to affirm of me. But having diſcharged that duty to my Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, I hope I may be allowed to lay the fault home upon my ſelf, and to tell you in all truth and ſincerity, that my tongue (I know not by what unhappy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper in delivering that meſſage) deliverd that which was never in my thoughts; ſo farr was I from thinking to deliver ſuch a meſſage from Sir <hi>R. T.</hi> that I proteſt I did not think my ſelf charg'd with any thing from him by way of meſſage. It is true, that being much mov'd at an ill office which had been done Sir R. <hi>T.</hi> I made a warm adreſs unto His Majeſty in his behalf, wherein I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſ'd his great grief that His Majeſty ſhould be offended with him, and having joyn'd thereunto ſome reaſonings of his, in juſtification of his Conduct, in order to His Majeſties ſervice, I purſued his expreſſions with ſuch others of mine own upon the ſame ſubject as, all circumſtances conſidered, any body but the King might eaſily have miſtaken, that to be a continuation of an adreſs from Sir R. <hi>T.</hi> and an undertaking of his, which was indeed a fervorous diſcourſe, and a confident undertaking of my own. Sir R. <hi>Temple</hi> being thus clear'd without the leaſt contraction to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>If undertaking for you Gentlemen be a gailt, 'tis only I that ſtand guilty before you, but you are too noble I am ſure and too juſt to condemn me in your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:171188:7"/>before you have heard the nature and circumſtances of my undertaking, which with your leave I ſhall now declare to you to the full taking the matter a I needs muſt to be rightly underſtood, from a higher original.</p>
            <p>Mr Speaker, Having had the honour heretofore to di charge with approbation a place of ſo high truſt as that of Secretary of State to His Majeſties Father of bleſſed memory, and himſelf, And ſince my quitting that place His Majeſty ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had the goodneſs to admit me frequently to the happineſs of his Princely converſation, you cannot imagine but that ſometimes he hath vouchſafed to ſpeak with me of ouſineſs eſpecially of Parliament, having the honour to be a Peer at preſent, and heretofore as much verſd as ſome of my contemporaries in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the honourable houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>I confeſs unto you Gentlemen, that before your laſt aſſembling he did it more then once; And the thing wherein I moſt conſtantly delivered my opinion concerning this honourable houſe was. That never King having been ſo happy in a houſe of Commons as he in you; A houſe compoſ'd of ſo many Gentlemen of birth, and fortune, eminent in their faithfulneſs to him, ſuch as could never be ſuſpected for any ſiniſter deſigns or any dependance but upon the Crown, and upon their duty to thoſe that choſe them, and ſuch as in the former ſeſſions had manifeſted their affections to him by ſuch large aids and ſupplies, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be more important to his ſervice then to make and preſerve you ſtill popular with thoſe that ſent you; To which end I took the liberty to tell him that if the neceſſity of his affairs (of which I that had no part in his Councell was no good Judge) could admit of it he ought not in prudence to let you give him any money this ſitting, But rather obliege you wholly to apply your ſelves to the making of ſuch Laws, as might endear both him and you to the people, and make them think that all that had been given well beſtowed, by which means at another meeting he would be maſter of the hearts and purſes of his ſubjects; But that in caſe his neceſſities ſhould urge him, to preſs you before your riſing for a new ſupply, That he ought by all means to let it be accompanied if not preceded by ſome eminent Acts, for reformation of former <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and for the ſecuring his ſubjects from the like for the future.</p>
            <p>I perſiſted, Mr. Speaker, in preſſing upon all occaſions; this advice to His Majeſty till ſome few weeks after your meeting, when as finding my ſelf, know not by what misfortune, fallen under ſome prejudices, I thought that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> total forbearance from ſpeaking to His Majeſty of any buſineſs would be the uſefulleſt way of ſerving him; And I do here proteſt unto you Gentlemen with all ſincerity, that from that time until this buſineſs of Sir R. <hi>T.</hi> I never once opened my lips to His Majeſty concerning any publick affair whatſoever.</p>
            <p>It is true Mr. Speaker. that a ground being given me to enter again with His Majeſty upon a ſubject which my heart was ſtill full of, I laid hold upon the occaſion, and in purſuance of what I had ſaid in behalf of Sir R. <hi>T.</hi> I told His Majeſty (perhaps with more freedome and fervour then became me) th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:171188:8"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eared his Courtiers gave him wrong meaſures both of the temper of the houſe of Commons, and of the means to obtain new ſupplies from them, whether by way of preſent gift, or of ſuch ſettlement in his revenue as might indeed bring him out of neceſſity, ſince that there could be no reaſonable hopes of obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any ſuch aſſiſtance, but by a concomitance at leaſt, if not a precedency of ſuch acts as might be grateful and beneficial to his ſubjects, and ſecure them, that what ſhould be given hereafter ſhould be better managed for his ſervice then thoſe vaſt ſumms that had been formerly granted. That if His Majeſty in his Princely wiſdome ſhould think fit to drive on his buſineſs upon ſuch ſolid grounds and not upon the falſe and ſelf-intreſted meaſures of ſome Courtiers, he had a houſe of Commons compoſed of members ſo full of affection to his perſon, and zeal for his proſperity and glory, That not only Sir <hi>Richard Temple,</hi> but the moſt unprejudiced and ableſt men in the Kingdom as well as my If durſt undertake That ſuch a houſe of Commons would neither let him want ſuch preſent ſupplies as the true neceſſities of his affairs ſhould require, or ſuch an eſtabliſhed revenue as was fit to ſupport the greatneſs and honour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Crown If this hath been a criminal undertaking, you have before you Gentlemen. <hi>Confitentem reum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Mr. Speaker, whilſt I am endeavouring to do right to Sir R. <hi>T.</hi> and to indicate or arraign my ſelf before you. according as you shall be pleaſed to underſtand it by telling you what paſſ'd from me to His Majeſty. I muſt not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to give the honour due to him, for the Kingly reply he made me upon that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, which was this.</p>
            <p>That he had a ſenſe of the affection and merit of the houſe of Commons to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, even beyond what I had expreſſ'd, and that was the reaſon why relying ſo intirely as he did upon the affections of that whole body, he was and should ever be offended at any propoſition to carry on his buſineſs there by officious undertakings and Cabals either of his Courtiers or others. An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ereſſion fit to be written with the rays of the Sun that all the world may read it: An expreſſion which certainly cannot but inflame the affections of this noble aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly that hears me. and carry you to make good thoſe happy impreſſions of you which are ſo deeply ſtamp'd in his Royal breaſt, ſuch as I should think it a crime <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> me to doubt; But that all ſuſpitions being now vanished of His Majeſties owing the ſupplies deſired to any arts or contrivances of others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> your own Zeal for his ſervice will, even in the proportion and timelineſs of that, exceed the vain propoſals of all Pick-thank undertakers.</p>
            <p>Mr, Speaker, I should here put a period to your trouble of hearing me, did not think I might incurr the imputation of much weakneſs and ſupineneſs in my own higheſt concernments, if valuing as I do above all earthly things the favour and eſteem of my Countrey, of which you are the illuſtrious repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive: And knowing what induſtry has been uſed by my enemies to blaſt me with you, I should not lay hold on this juſt occaſion, to remove from me
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171188:8"/>unjuſt prejudices with ſo great an object of my veneration. 'Tis that Mr. Speaker, which I humbly beg leave to do in a very few words more.</p>
            <p>I appeal Gentlemen to numbers of you that hear me, whether I have not been repreſented unto you for a giver of advices of a farr different tenor from what you have heard upon this occaſion; Nay whether I have not been painted out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you as an inflamer of His Majeſty againſt his Parliament, As an enemy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and as a moſt dangerous driver on of Papiſtical intereſts.</p>
            <p>It is true Mr. Speaker, I am a <hi>Catholick</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> not of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> no negotiator there of Cardinals Caps for His Majeſties ſubject and Domeſticks. A true <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> as to the other world. but a true <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> as to this. Such a one, as had we a King enclined to that profeſſion (as on the contrary we have one the moſt firm and zealous in the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that ever fare upon the Throne) should tell him as frankly as the Duke of <hi>Sully</hi> being a Proteſtant did to his Grand-father <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, That if he meant to be King he muſt be a conſtant profeſſor and maintainer of the religion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh'd in his Dominions. Believe me Gentlemen, <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> as I am there is no man among you all more throughly perſwaded then I, that the two Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars that can only uphold this Monarchy muſt ever be, the maintenance of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects juſt rights and liberties, and the careful preſervation of that ſtate eccleſiaſtical whereof His Majeſty is the ſupreme governour. And I do cleerly profeſs that ſhould the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf invade that eſtablish'd right of his, I would as readily draw my Sword againſt him as againſt the late uſurper.</p>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, One prejudice more I am under, which ought to have great weight indeed with this honourable houſe if there be a real ground for it, and that is. That the Earle of <hi>Briſtol</hi> is one of thoſe, who by the vaſt things he hath got of the King, hath in part contributed to the groans of the people to find their King ſtill in ſuch neceſſity after ſuch unexampled charges laid upon the ſubject for his ſupply.</p>
            <p>It is true Mr. Speaker, That though I have neither office to keep, nor office to ſell, His Majeſties gifts to me have been great in proportion to my merit which is none; For in ſerving and ſuffering for him with faithfulneſs. I did but my duty, which carries a reward with it ſelf enough to raiſe comfort to me from the very ruine of my fortune.</p>
            <p>It is alſo true I have had the ſatisfaction from His Majeſties goodneſs, That he never refuſ'd me any thing that I ask'd him for my ſelf, But I hope I ſhall make it appear alſo, That I have not only been a very modeſt asker, but alſo a moſt careful one to ask nothing conſiderable but what carried advantage with it as well to His Majeſties Intereſts as my own.</p>
            <p>I know well Mr. Speaker, that ſo kind and ſo generous a nature as our Kings is an ill proportioner of bounty to merit, and conſequently that the largeneſs and kindneſs of his Royal heart that way may have contributed much to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtraits he is in.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:171188:9"/>
Happy the Nation who hath nothing to fear for the Publique, but from the vertues of their Prince.</p>
            <p>It is your proper work Gentlemen to reduce the effects of them to a right temperament by your inſpection, and may you begin it with all my concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which I moſt readily lay at your feet, humbly begging of you to appoint me a time when I may diſplay them all faithfully before you, in hopes that no man who hath been a partaker of His Majeſties bounty will prove himſelf ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of it as not to follow the example.</p>
            <p>Mr. Speaker, If having thus powred out my ſoul before you I be ſo happy as to have begot a right perſwaſion in this honourable houſe of the true ſincerity of my heart, I ſhall expect and implore two gratious effects of it.</p>
            <p>The firſt, that you will be pleaſed to grant me your pardon, if the ſame zeal for His Majeſties ſervice, and the good of my Countrey, which made me preſume (being no Counſellor) to preſs upon him my opinion in affairs of that impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance have tranſported me alſo at this time to become in ſome ſort your adviſer.</p>
            <p>You have heard Mr. Speaker, of the dumb man whoſe tongue was ſet free by an iminent danger to his Fathers life, wonder not then Gentlemen if ſuch a lover of my King and Counnrey as I am, remembring to have ſeen them both, within theſe three years in a Proſpect of ſo much glory and happineſs both at home and abroad, and finding to what a ſad condition things are now reduced (by what means is more proper for your wiſdom's to examine) and God in Heaven bleſs your inſpection, wonder not I ſay that a man ſo affected as I am, ſhould by ſome coruptions of heart let you ſee, that <hi>Periculum patriae</hi> ought to have a more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful effect upon a man of a Publique ſoul, then <hi>Periculum patris,</hi> and is capable if I were a mute to make me become a Counſellor.</p>
            <p>The next is Mr. Speaker, That if as I ſaid before, I have been ſo happy in what I have expreſſed, as to have raiſed in you ſome more favourable thoughts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning me, you will vouchſafe me ſome demonſtration of it, whereby I may no more be made by my enemies ſuch a Bug-bear as I am, as if one gratious look of His Majeſty upon me were enough to ruine all his affairs with you, I ſhall then Mr. Speaker, continue the courſe I am in with comfort. But if I be ſo unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate as that there ſtill remains in this incomparable repreſentative of my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey the leaſt umbrage of danger to it by my acceſs to His Majeſty. As dear as the converſation of the moſt amiable Prince that ever breathd is to me, I ſhall baniſh my ſelf for ever from his ſight into the obſcureſt part of his Dominions, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then continue upon <hi>me</hi> the jealouſie of thoſe upon whom his proſperity de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends. Or if this be not enough, I ſhall once more try my fortune abroad, where truſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Sword, this Head, and this Heart, ſhall make me live again as I have done in ſpight of mine enemies, with luſter to <hi>my</hi> ſelf, and ſome honour to <hi>my</hi> Nation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
